Finding Aid for Louis H. Sullivan architectural drawings, 1875-1922
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis H. Sullivan architectural drawings 1875-1922
Sullivan, Louis H., 1856-1924.
1 folder (photocopies); 2 boxes (framed originals)
92961 Aa 1
American architect. Pencil drawings of architectural ornament details, preliminary drawings for the Merchants National Bank, Grinnell, Iowa, and early humor and figure studies; also manuscript, 1922, entitled, "The Chicago Tribune Competition."
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The materials were found in the papers of Professor Emil Lorch (donor no. 4041 ). Provenance is otherwise unknown.
The collection is open to research, but because of the fragility of the individual items, the library has restricted access to the originals (except with special permission). There are photocopies and photographic prints of every item in the collection.
American architect, born Sept. 3, 1856 in Boston, Massachusetts. He studied architecture under William Ware and Eugene Letang at Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Sullivan moved to Chicago in 1873 and obtained work with William LeBaron Jenney. Studied at the Ecole de Beaus-Arts in Paris for brief time in 1874 before returning to Chicago where he worked as a draftsman in the office of Joseph S. Johnston & John Edelman. In 1879 Sullivan joined the firm of Dankmar Adler and by 1883 had become a partner in the firm of Adler & Sullivan. The firm designed over 180 buildings during its existence, primarily residential, and office buildings. The firm employed a number of young draftsmen and architects--Frank Lloyd Wright, George Elmslie and William Purcell-- who, influenced by Sullivan's philosophy, would develop the Prairie Style of architecture. Adler left the firm in 1895. Sullivan's practice began to decline over the next five years but he did complete one of his most famous designs for the Schlesinger and Mayer department store (later Carson, Pirie, Scott) in Chicago. After the turn of the century Sullivan's practice consisted mainly of small banks and commercial buildings in the Midwest, most notably the Farmer's National Bank in Owatanna, Minnesota. Sullivan died April 14, 1924.
Pencil drawings of architectural ornament details, preliminary drawings for the Merchants National Bank, Grinnell, Iowa, and early humor and figure studies; also manuscript, 1922, entitled, "The Chicago Tribune Competition." This collection was accumulated by University of Michigan architecture professor Emil Lorch.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Architecture.; Merchants National Bank (Grinnell, Iowa); Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Cartoons.; Drawings.
- Louis Sullivan drawings
  (photocopies; originals in the BHL vault)
  - Architectural ornament/Horse, undated, H: 7 1/2" W: 12 1/2"; collage: two-sided drawing. Tracing paper with graphite pencil drawing attached to one side; Straight graphite pencil on the other. (Folder 1)
    (copy negatives available na7070 na12,752)
  - Comical sketch of man and woman with inscription, 1875, H: 12" W: 8 1/4 " Rectangular Drawing: Pen and ink on tracing paper. (Folder 1)
    (copy negative available na8185)
  - Architectural ornaments, 1875-1876, H: 5" W: 6"; Six sketches on four notebook pages, notebook in graphite pencil on mould made of paper with blue lines; the pieces have been cut out of a notebook, and parts of the inscription are lost. (Folder 1)
    (copy negative available na7064-na7069)
  - Merchants National Bank, Grinnell, Iowa, 1913, H: 11"W:8 3/8" Three preliminary architectural drawings: floor plans, 4th Ave. elevation, Broad St. elevation. Graphite pencil on yellow wove. The paper is pharmaceutical prescription paper, of The Storm Pharmacy, Grinnell, Iowa. (Folder 1)
    (copy negatives available na3156 and na3763 (duplicates), na3157 and na3764 (duplicates), na3158 na8184 na8183)
  - Ornament design, 1881, H: 12" W: 8 1/4 "; Rectangular Drawing: Graphite pencil on wove paper. (Folder 1)
    (copy negative available na8182)
  - Head of Girl, 1885, H: 7" W: 10 1/4"; Rectangular Drawing: Graphite pencil on wove paper. (Folder 1)
    (copy negative available na7073)
  - Female Figure Nude, 1879, H: 12 3/4" W: 8 1/4"; Rectangular Drawing: Graphite pencil on wove paper. (Folder 1)
    (copy negative available na7074)
  - Architectural ornament, undated, Collage: two sided octahedral-shaped drawing. Graphite pencil drawing on wove card stock. Three pieces tracing paper with pencil drawing glued to recto, one piece glued to verso. (Folder 1)
    (copy negatives available na7071, na7072)
  - Manuscript entitled "The Chicago Tribune Competition," 1922 (Folder 1)